<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mr. Keith's sermon, preach'd on May the 12th, 1700. At Dr. Bedford's church, being Saint George Butolphs-Lane, by Billings-Gate. On Luke the 1st and verse 6th.</title>
            <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B03937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R179321</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981670</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981670</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180263</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B03937)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180263)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2824:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mr. Keith's sermon, preach'd on May the 12th, 1700. At Dr. Bedford's church, being Saint George Butolphs-Lane, by Billings-Gate. On Luke the 1st and verse 6th.</title>
                  <author>Keith, George, 1639?-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and sold by most booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"You are to take notice, this is the genuine copy"--t.p.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke I, 6 --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines --  Sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180263:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Keith's</hi> SERMON, Preach'd on <hi>May</hi> the 12th, 1700. At Dr. <hi>Bedford</hi>'s Church, BEING Saint <hi>George's Butolphs-Lane, </hi> by <hi>Billings-Gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KE</hi> the <hi>1ſt.</hi> and Verſe <hi>6th.</hi>
               <q>And they were both Righteous before GOD, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the LORD Blameleſs.</q>
            </p>
            <p>☞ You are to take Notice, this is the Genuine Copy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the AUTHOR; and Sold by moſt Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:180263:2"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>George Keith</hi>'s SERMON, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>LUKE, <hi>1ſt.</hi> Chap: Verſ. 6.</bibl>
                  <p>And they were both Righteous before God, walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU have an Account of a Prieſt, or Teacher, with his Wife, both which being ancient, and as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> here ſaith, <hi>Righteous</hi> too <hi>before God, walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances blameleſs;</hi> yet for all thoſe gay pretences, the Man was turned Infidel, and did, or at leaſt could not believe the Commands and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Lord; and ſo in Juſtice was ſtricken Dumb, becauſe he did not believe God's Words, which ſhall be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in their ſeaſon, <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. Now in taking my leave of my Old and well-Beloved Friends, namely the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> to which I was once joyned, and made (as <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias</hi> was) a Teacher among them; and (according to their and my weak Opinion) righteous before God, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in (as they and I thought) all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But ſince growing in Years, ſo in Knowledge too, being I hope (as <hi>Zacharias</hi> was) better inſtructed by the bleſſed Spirit <hi>Gabriel,</hi> which ſtands in the Preſence of God, and ſo comes from him to bring as glad-tydings to me as it did to <hi>Zacharias,</hi> to ſtrike me for my Infidelity, Dumb; and not able to ſpeak until the time be accompliſhed, or fulfilled in their Seaſons, <hi>verſ.</hi> 19, 20. And <hi>ſome People <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ted for the man</hi> Zacharias, <hi>and marvelled;</hi> but <hi>when he came out he could not ſpeak to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now you, my <hi>dearly Beloved,</hi> with whom I now travail in this New Birth, to apply this to my ſelf, and you for
<pb facs="tcp:180263:2"/>
your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, you are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Spou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> nay, and alſo as we then thought, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fore God, walking in all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Lord blameleſs: but finde it has pleaſed the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to ſend to me his bleſſed Spirit, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not duty my but your Infidelity alſo, that we have not been ſo Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous as we ſhould have been, as to have had Conſciences<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> always void of Offence both towards God and Man; neither have we walked in the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blameleſs: And ſince God Almighty ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as he did to <hi>Zacharias)</hi> been pleaſed to ſend his bleſſed Spirit to diſcover our Errors, (which I muſt confeſs were like to the <hi>Jews</hi> altogether through Ignorance, and ſo I hope pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able) and to ſhew thoſe glad Tydings, <hi>viz.</hi> what the real Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord are, that we may walk in them and be blameleſs.</p>
            <p>And ſince for my Infidelity, the All-wiſe God ſuffered me to be ſtruck Dumb, till the accompliſhed Time and Seaſon, which I hope and find is now; for you are not ignorant that thoſe People, before mentioned, which both you and I had, (being then joyned to) had, (and I hope ſtill have) a tenderneſs for; they I ſay, for my Infidelity, by God's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſtruck me Dumb: So that both in <hi>Penſtlvania</hi> and here, I being Anathamatized, or Excommunicated by them, became as it were to them Dumb, and Speechleſs; at which you and ſome others which waited upon me there, marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as thoſe did at <hi>Zacharias,</hi> verſ. 21, 22, 23. thinking and truly ſuppoſing that I (as he) had ſeen a Viſion, or Spirit, which made me, as it did him (depart from them) to his, and mine own Houſe; So that it is no Myſtery nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to them nor you, that I was obliged to Teach and Inſtruct privately in Holes and in Corners, as in this little <hi>Hall,</hi> &amp;c. But thanks be to God, being by the bleſſed Spirit better inſtructed in Righteouſneſs in general, and in all the Commands and Ordinances of the Lord, to be without ſpot or blame; the Time being accompliſhed, and my Tongue looſed, to ſpeak of the Righteouſneſs towards Man as well as God, and to walk not as you and I have formerly, not only Ignorantly, but Obſtinately, and Maliciouſly in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:180263:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in all) of the Commandments and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord Blameleſs.</p>
            <p>And now having by the aforeſaid Spirit, had a Call to the true Church, which I find has a Righteouſneſs to Men as well as God, and walks in and keeps not only ſome, but all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, I muſt humbly and heartily take leave of this private Place herein Errors have been both (as I muſt ſincerely confeſs ignorantly, and wilfully broached and taught; but I neither ſhall, nor will take leave of you my <hi>dearly Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> for whom I have been as it were in Bonds, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed, and do now travail that both you and I reſorting, and fleeing to the true Church as a Sanctuary, may with old <hi>Zacharias,</hi> verſ. 68. to the 80th. Bleſs the Lord God which hath viſited and redeemed us his People, by raiſing up an Horn of Salvation for us, that we ſhould be ſaved from our Enemies, and from the Hand of all that hate us, to ſerve him for the future without fear, in <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before Him all the Days of our Lives;</hi> for having given a better knowledge of <hi>Salvation</hi> unto us his People, by the <hi>Remiſſion of our Sins,</hi> through the tender <hi>Mercy of our God,</hi> whereby the <hi>Day-ſpring from on High hath viſited us,</hi> to give Light to them (that is others of our <hi>Friends</hi> that are left behind) that now (as we once did) <hi>ſit in Darkneſs, and in the ſhadow of Death,</hi> and to <hi>guide both their and our Feet into the Way of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus having explained the Text, by declaring and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring Old <hi>Zacharias</hi>'s Condition with mine own, I come now from the Words ſo read: <hi>Firſt,</hi> To declare what the True Church is; which may eaſily be diſcovered by the Infallible Marks following. <hi>Secondly,</hi> What that Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is, which makes, and will make any blameleſs. And, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What the Commandments of God were and are. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> What Ordinances the Lord has appointed in his Church, that all true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may walk in, and ſo obſerve and keep them, ſo as to be blameleſs; and then ſhall make ſome Inferences, and Applications from, and of what I have ſaid, <hi>&amp;c.—</hi>True, ſince amidſt the great diverſity and contrariety of Opinions, which at preſent are in the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> each entitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing it ſelf to the true Faith,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:180263:3"/>
which as St. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeem a matter of extream <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> true Faith of the Goſpel: Yet I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that the difficulty doth not ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the thing, as it doth from Men and Womens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Intereſts and Affections, in diſputing about the <hi>Faith:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore abſtracting from theſe, I ſhall now <hi>firſt,</hi> by <hi>God's</hi> aſſiſtance, endeavour to ſet before you the chief <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racters of a True Goſpel Faith,</hi> by which you may judge what the <hi>True Church</hi> is, and where it is to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: Now a <hi>Goſpel Faith</hi> is an Ancient <hi>Primitive Faith</hi> for <hi>Truth</hi> you know was from the beginning; yea, divers of the Doctrines with which our <hi>Saviour</hi> enlightened thoſe that came to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> were from the <hi>Moral Law,</hi> before his Perſonal Appearance: for as he well ſaid, <hi>Abraham ſaw his Day,</hi> (that it) his great Truths and Ways<hi>:</hi> For our <hi>Bleſſed Lord</hi> was the Author and Finiſher of our Faith, in him it begun, and was conſumated in his Perſonal Teachings and Inſtructions of his immediate Diſciples and Apoſtles, who by the unerring guide, <hi>viz.</hi> The Spirit left to us what they had received from him. True, natural Truths are more and more diſcovered by Time; for many go too and fro, ſo that Science is increaſed: But the Divine Truths are moſt perfect in their Fountain, and Original, they indeed may, and do contract Impurities in their Streams, and remote Derivations. So that the way to diſcover the <hi>Corruptions,</hi> is to ſtand upon the old Ways, and ſee how it was in the Original or Beginning, whether that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> which is taught, is to <hi>Man</hi> as well as to <hi>God:</hi> For a good <hi>Conſcience</hi> muſt and ſhould be always void of Offence towards both; and whether their walking is, and has been in all the <hi>Commandments</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances</hi> of the Lord or no? if it has but been only in ſome, and not in all, verily it cannot, nay, muſt not be accounted blameleſs. So by this firſt and true Character of a true <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Faith,</hi> two very dangerous Extreams are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; as <hi>firſt,</hi> that of the now <hi>Roman Church,</hi> whoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Uſages, which are truly denyed by that <hi>Church</hi> to which I am now joyned; theſe following are in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, Novelties and Innovations, viz. their <hi>Image Worſhip, Innovations of Saints, Half Communion, Prayer in an unknown</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:180263:4"/>
               <hi>Tongue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Infalliability,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſality,</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which whatſoever they pretend to<hi>:</hi> I can aſſure you, many of the Learned Divines of the Church to which I adhere, have proved that all the before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, were generally unknown in the <hi>Firſt,</hi> and <hi>pureſt Times</hi> and ſo muſt be contrary to a <hi>Goſpel Faith</hi> and <hi>True Church.</hi> The <hi>Second</hi> on the other Extream is, that <hi>Faith</hi> of the moſt of the New Sects is to be Condemned, becauſe of its No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty, and Innovation: For where was <hi>Presbytery, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, Anabaptiſm</hi> and <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> of Old? True, I muſt confeſs that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e were ſome ſuch like Hereſies ſwiming in the Brains of ſome Ignorant, but Conceited Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men then; yet never as we Read were they in any general Practiſe any where: For the Eldeſt we Read of, were not above Three Hundred Years ago; and ſome have ſprung up even in this laſt Century or Age; which to my Sorrow and Shame, I muſt confeſs my ſelf to have been of: and to have grown and ſprung up even from Mine, and others ſickle Fancys, and vain Imaginations: And God knows how ſoon, now even amongſt ſuch, and ſo many Confuſions, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new yet unheard of <hi>Sects,</hi> and <hi>Hereſies</hi> may ariſe, and all to the further dividing of the true Church by Law Eſtabliſhed, and the ſcandal of <hi>Chriſtian Faith</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>True, all Theſe like the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> may profeſs a great many Truths of the Goſpel Faith, yet for all that, (as their's had) may have too much Leaven to ſpoil the whole Lump: But as the true Faith was of Old, ever from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: So <hi>Secondly,</hi> it was, and is to be both Pure, and Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; for St. <hi>James</hi> 3. 17. Aſſures us, <hi>that Wiſdom or Truth, which is from above, is firſt Pure, than Peaceable, Gentle, and eaſie to be intreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits; without Partiality and without Hypocriſie: teaching and producing Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Holineſs, and Righteouſneſs in Life and Heart:</hi> For the buſineſs of it both was, and is to conform us unto Chriſt, and to make us Holy as he was; and that in all manner of our Converſations, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 15, 16. And not only Holy, but Peaceable alſo; for Chriſt was the Prince of Peace, and his Goſpel the Goſpel of Peace, and not of Confuſion, as is manifeſted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 24. from the 33. to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:180263:4"/>
end. <hi>For God is not the Author of Confuſion, but of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> As in all Churches of the Saints, let your Women keep Silen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the Churches, for it is not permitted them to Speak: but theſe are Commanded to be under Obedience, as alſo ſaith the Law,</hi> &amp;c. By which ſecond Character of a true Church, there are likewire theſe two aforeſaid dangerous Extreams, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and Confuted<hi>:</hi> The firſt of which, <hi>viz.</hi> Popery, which apparently teaches not only direct Impieties, and Immoralities, by the conſequences of its Doctrines; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo endeavours to Deſtroy both, Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Peace. For <hi>Firſt,</hi> by their Idollatries, and Invocation of Saints and Angels; which by the Prophets and Apoſtles, is termed Spiritual Fornication and Whoredom, by Diſhon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouring God's Majeſty, and Affronting his Glory: Theſe then muſt undoubtedly be accounted great Impieties; and likewiſe their Doctrines and Practices of Depoſing and Murthering Princes, by abſolving People from their Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and diſpencing with their Perjuries and Rebellions: all which are verily high Immortalities, and clear contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Spirit, and deſign of the Holy Jeſus, which came to redeem unto himſelf a Peculiar People, zealous of good Works: Nay, beſides theſe, they even ſtrike at the Root and main Deſign of Chriſtianity, by theſe following Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, which renders Repentance, and Change of Life unneceſſary. For as they think, ſo are apt to believe, that the Favour of God, and Eternal Salvation, may be had upon eaſier Terms; namely, Croſſes, Pilgrimages, <hi>Ave Marias,</hi> Whipings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Faſtings often, with a bare Confeſſion and Abſolution: They (I ſay) do not only think, but alſo really believe, that theſe will do their Buſineſs; or if theſe will not, but to <hi>Pugatory</hi> they muſt go<hi>:</hi> Yet theſe ſuppoſe, and verily believe, that if they can but procure Money enough to leave for ſuch a number of <hi>Maſſes</hi> and <hi>Dirgies;</hi> then they ſhall be ſecured of being Prayed out thence<hi>:</hi> So that the greateſt deſign of the Goſpel, which is real inward Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, is Deſtroyed by them; for they never ſo much as think of a Neceſſity of Cutting off right Hands, and pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out Eyes, that is of Subduing, and reſcinding an inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Appetites and Affections, which are the great di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Religion; Theſe they account hard Sayings, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:180263:5"/>
cannot endure either to hear of or practiſe them: Nay, more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er as for their Unpeaceable Tempers, and Behaviours, both in Spiritual and Temporal, concerns that's Manifeſted, not only from our own, but Forreign Hiſtories. And the other dangerous Extream is, there are many Sects which Forſooth pretend (as I once did to my Shame be it ſpoken) to Purity and Spirituality<hi>:</hi> Saying, <hi>That God ſees no Sin in his Saints or Elect, they be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng without Sin, a Precious and Choice People;</hi> yea, affirming, <hi>That God loves not for the ſake of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Vertue, but freely</hi> (i. e.) <hi>for no reaſon, but meer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable Will:</hi> And if it be ſo, then it's in vain for any to amend their Lives, or to live Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly, in order to their acceptance with God: tho' they are contrary in all manner of Converſation; (as may be inferr'd from their Doctrine) yet theſe have been taught, and ſo fondly think that by being God's Choſen, or Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, they ſhall be ſaved, which abominable and abſurd Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, has not only the Malignity of the worſt of <hi>Popery,</hi> but of Heatheniſm too; for it makes good Works unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> True, they have a Faith indeed, but it's very Airy, which is only a receiving, truſting, and relying upon Chriſt by, and in which they do well, being parts of true Faith: But even this the Devils have, and practiſe, which as St. <hi>James</hi> 2. 19. 26. tells us, is Dead, and Inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant alone, to the purpoſe of Juſtification, and Acceptance with God.</p>
            <p>Nay, Further you know, that the imputed Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, is a great Truth, rightly underſtood: But ſome Sects abuſe it to this falſe Notion, that all the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs which Chriſt wrought, is formerly and properly theirs, as if they themſelves had done it. So they fondly think that by Chriſt's Holineſs, they can, and are made Holy and Righteous, tho' they have none of their own: All which is apparently contrary to that in St. <hi>John</hi> 3. 9. <hi>Liltle Children let no Man deceive you: He that doth Righteouſneſs, is Righteous.</hi> So theſe which I have mentioned, that have ſuch Solifidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an and Antinomian Notions, by placing (as I did once) their Religion in the Fancy, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do theirs, in ſome External Services; do both effectually take away the neceſſity of a real Reformation, and true Goodneſs. Nay,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:180263:5"/>
I might add a great many more ſuch as their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Infirmities; by which they are apt to excuſe themſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in their Spiritual Sins, and their Decrying Moraiity, as a dull, low, Graceleſs Thing; crying up the Immoral pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of Schiſme and Diſobedience, which they indulge, and defend themſelves in. True, I muſt confeſs that there are many miſled, abuſed Perſons, of peaceable and quiet Spirits among theſe Sectaries: So that we as Chriſtians are to pray, and endeavour that ſuch may be regained. And in all Humble ſubmiſſion to my Goverours, If the Grand Council the next Seſſions, thinks fit to abate ſome leſſer things in Conſideration of ſuch, verily it would (in my weak Judgment in all Chriſtian Countries) be eſteemed Charity and Kindneſs, which I am confident no true Chriſtian either would, or could diſlike: But alas, I am not inſenſible that thoſe which are of the right Sectarian Stamp and Temper, will (as I formerly did) never reſt or ſettle any where, nor be ſatisfied with any Conceſſion: God Almighty indeed may change their Minds by his Power: But I am afraid nothing leſs can. So that all, both you, and I, and others of our Church can, and muſt do, is only to pray to God for the Converſion of ſuch. For we have found, and I have ſome Reaſon to think may now find again, as it's feared by woful Experience, that nothing leſs than the whole Wills of ſome, and an entire Subjection to their Fancies, have or will content them: for if ſuch were granted all, as they were formerly, we cannot be aſſured that theſe would pleaſe long; only this we know, that formerly they did not; nay, as St. <hi>Jude</hi> in his Epiſtle, <hi>ver.</hi> 12. ſaith, ſuch a Whimſicall and Diſcontented People, are as Clouds without Water, carried about with every Wind<hi>:</hi> For it is certain, that let the Wind be where it will to Day, none can ſay from what Point it will blow to Morrow; juſt thus, as ſuch a People acted by their private Spirit, (as God knows I was once) which is, as obſerved as little, certain as the Wind; for (as I have found by woful Experience) the Opinions it ſuggeſts, are numerous, and all accounted Divine and Sacred, <hi>viz. Goſpel-Truths, Goſpel-Ways,</hi> which forſooth, muſt not be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with: No, in no wiſe<hi>:</hi> Yea, all Laws and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Government</hi> muſt be thwarted, and overthrown ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb facs="tcp:180263:6"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d all muſt be Sacrificed to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Imaginations</hi> of ſuch. Oh<hi>!</hi> what Bleſſed Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and Days can we expect thence? What Peace and Temper have ſprung from ſuch Principles, the Hiſtories of <hi>Germany, England,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> make us remember for caution only: So I heartily wiſh, that no ſuch People in this Age, did or would not remember them ſo well, as to put them in Practiſe, which if they do, we have no refuge but to uſe that daily Petition, and ſay, <hi>Father not ours, but thy Will be done in Earth, as it is in Heaven.</hi> Which brings me to the <hi>Third</hi> and <hi>Laſt</hi> particular Mark or Sign, to know a true Church by, and that is, that all which it commands, is both Reaſonable and Certain, which the Wiſeman al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes to <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 27. <hi>That the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of Man, is the Candle of the Lord, the Light of Reaſon is his Light;</hi> with that the true Light hath enlightned every one that cometh into the World: And now one Light ſhould not be contrary to the other; there is, I muſt confeſs, a difference in degree, but no oppoſition of Nature, ſo Faith and Reaſon accord: Yea, Faith is an act of Reaſon, for it's the higheſt Reaſon to believe in God, and the belief of our Reaſon, is an act of <hi>Faith, viz. Faith</hi> in the <hi>Truth</hi> and goodneſs of <hi>God,</hi> which gives no Man faculties to delude or deceive him: If ſo be he doth but rightly Exerciſe and Employ them; yea, by Faith, Reaſon is further enlightned, and by the uſe of Reaſon, Faith is applyed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>true Religion,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſweetly agree<hi>:</hi> For nothing can be Religious that is unreaſonable, which made the great Apoſtle call the Chriſtian Religion a <hi>Reaſonable Service;</hi> Yea, ſo certain is the true <hi>Faith,</hi> that thoſe which had it from the Holy Spirit of <hi>God,</hi> Signed it with their Blood, theſe ſpeaking as they were inſpired: and that they were really ſo, was no fond <hi>Imagination,</hi> or bold <hi>Preſumption:</hi> But a <hi>Truth</hi> aſſured by theſe mighty Miracles they were enabled to perform. Theſe are God's Seal, and a grand <hi>Confirmation</hi> of a <hi>Commiiſſon</hi> from him, and to that proof of their <hi>Doctrines</hi> both <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> continually Appealed. Here was, and is then the firm reaſonable Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Chriſtian certainty: the Truths we are to believe, were confirmed by <hi>Miracles,</hi> than which there can
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:180263:6"/>
be no greater Evidence by which laſt Character theſe two before cited dangerous Extreams, are Diſpiſed and Condemned: As <hi>Firſt,</hi> that of <hi>Popery,</hi> which impoſeth on the Minds of Men as Articles of <hi>Religion,</hi> things that are both Extream Unreaſonable, Abſurd, and Uncertain, <hi>viz.</hi> Theſe namely, the Worſhipping of inviſible Beings by Images of Wood, Stone, or ſome Mettal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but more eſpecially that Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which is full of Contradictions: Since the aſſerting that the ſame Body may be in a Thouſand places at once; and that it may be divided into Parts, tho' not into wholes Theſe and a numerous other Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities to the Reaſon of Mankind, are contained in that ſenſeleſs Myſtery of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> to defend which their <hi>Doctors</hi> have been, and are forced to deny Reaſon, and ſay that the ſame thing may, and can be, and not be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Beloved,</hi> if neither Reaſon, nor ſo much as our Senſes may be believed; Pray what aſſurance can we have of any thing? But Oh! What aſſurance had <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> to ſtrengthen his ſtaggering Faith about our Saviour's Reſurrection? This only, and that particularly from his Lord, <hi>viz. Stretch out thine hand and thruſt it into my ſide, and be not faithleſs, but believing.</hi> Nay, further, the now <hi>Roman Church</hi> deſtroys the Ground of Certainty, by an innumerable Company of Lying Wonders; which you may Read of in their <hi>Legends,</hi> which the Prieſts do impudently obtrude upon the belief of the ſilly and ignorant People only for proof, and confirmation of their Religion. But on the other Hand, the Sects and Sepratiſts being in as dangerous an Extream concerning Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For I found, and have now juſt Reaſon to acknowledge, that the greateſt part of my Religion, when among them, was made up of ſenſeleſs and abſurd Notions, (which I am now aſhamed of) they being (as we were wont) ſet forth in unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligible fantaſtical Phraſes; by (as 2 <hi>Pet</hi> 3. 16. ſaith) wreſting of Scriptures to our own Deſtruction: tho' I indeed then, (as well as they) accounted it, the heights of Spirituality and Myſtery, upon which we valued and boaſted our ſelves, as the only Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Spiritual People: When as Thanks be to God, it is known now to me, and all diſcerning Perſons that there was, and is nothing in ſuch pretended Heights and Spiritualities, but only vain Imagination and Dreaming; which are dangerous Deceits. For as the Light of Reaſon and Senſe diſpels the vain Images of Dreams: So theſe admitted, would and will cure all Phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Impoſtures and Deluſions, for which cauſe they, as well as I, formerly declared againſt nothing ſo vehemently as Reaſon, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of Carnal, and ſo an Enemy to the Spirit; and the things of it. True, I muſt needs confeſs now, that there is a Carnal Reaſon which is Enmity to Truth and Goodneſs: But that (as I am rightly inform'd) is not the Reaſon of our Minds,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:180263:7"/>
but our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, Paſſions, and corrupt Intereſts; which is not Reaſon truly and properly ſo call'd; no more than an <hi>Ape</hi> can be call'd a <hi>Man:</hi> And for want of knowing, and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things which ſo differ. Verily, <hi>Enthuſiaſticks</hi> rail vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently againſt all Reaſon, as the grand Adverſary of the Truths and Myſterys of the Goſpel. Nay, further reſolving as I did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, all aſſurance either into, or upon a bare belief of the Teſtimony of a private Spirit: For as mine was, ſo their Ground and Belief of the Scriptures both was, and is this Teſtimony; and conſequently whatſoever is received from hence, bottoms there. The <hi>Papiſts,</hi> as it's confeſt, believe the Scriptures on the Teſtimony of their Church, but that Sect of which I was with others, believe them on the Teſtimony of their Spirit: That is in Sober Sadneſs, by the Suggeſtions, and Reſolutions of their own, <hi>viz.</hi> they (like ſilly Women led Captive) believe becauſe they will believe, finding themſelve inclined to it: So up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame Reaſon as has been obſerved; when the Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Humour (as mine did) alters, they then may, and will ceaſe to believe; or as I do now believe the contrary: I ſhall not appeal only to my own Experience, but to that in others alſo. For have not ſome vaſtly multiplyed Articles of Faith, by making all their private Opinions ſacred, calling them Goſpel, and ſaving Truths; whereas at the beſt they were but uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: For being ſenſeleſs Imaginations, they are uſually falſe, by which they expoſe the whole Body of Chriſtian Principles to Suſpicion, and ſo weaken the Faith of ſome, and deſtroy that of others. So now having given you the Characters of a true Church; Namely <hi>Firſt,</hi> that its Articles of Faith and Doctrine are antient, <hi>viz.</hi> as St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith, <hi>That which was once delivered to the Saints. Secondly,</hi> That it's Pure, and Peaceable: And <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> That thoſe things it commands, are both reaſonable and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: And ſince for all the fine and gay Pretences, I cannot find ſuch a Faith in theſe two dangerous Extreams, which I have fairly and impartially Examined: I will by God's aſſiſtance Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, and ſee whether that Church, into which I am now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, being by Law Eſtabliſhed, has thoſe Marks and Characters of a true Faith, which I have before deſcribed: And <hi>Firſt,</hi> I am well aſſured, and ſo dare boldly aſſert, that the Church Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without fondneſs, or over-weaning, doth profeſs, and teach the antient Primitive, and Apoſtolick Faith, having admitted no new things that are contrary to it: For it was reformed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, and the Apoſtolick Rules, and Ways: I ſay according to the Scriptures, as they were interpreted by the firſt General Councils and Fathers; thoſe I mean next to the Apoſtles, whom we ought to believe; for they then aſſuredly underſtood what was the Apoſtles Doctrines, and Ways; nay,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:180263:7"/>
the Church is truly and rightly called <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Sectarian</hi> Innovations; ſo according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Character muſt be true.<hi>—Secondly,</hi> It teaches us Righteouſneſs in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, namely our duty to <hi>God,</hi> our Neighbours, and our Selves, in the juſt Latitude and extent of them: For it has no Shifts, and Evaſions of Repentance and Reformation; it allows no hopes of Salvation but upon Goſpel terms: It teaches no Practiſe that is either Impious, or Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, nor indulgeth any by its Doctrine; perhaps ſome Rotten Members may wink, and connive at ſuch: For the Church it ſelf tells us that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is Evil, muſt know it, by being Judged and Condemned: Nay, further, the Church leaves no hopes of Salvation, but what is grounded on effectual Repentance, and Reformation; nor impoſeth any Articles of belief, as neceſſary to Salvation, but the antient Creed, and no terms of Communion; but reaſonable Orders and Decencies, as are free from all appearance of Idolatry and Superſtition, or any thing elſe that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unlawful; and as to the concerns of civil Peace, the Church with Chriſt and his Apoſtles hath taught all active, Chearful and Conſcientious Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, both to God, the King, and alſo Subordinate Rulers in all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things, and a quiet Submiſſion to the Penalties of not Obeying, when the things required, are plainly or certainly ſo, to its former Praiſe, Renown, and Happineſs, be it ſpoken. So <hi>Laſtly,</hi> the Church now Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, teaches no Opinions that needs ſuch a deſperate Courſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them: For all its Articles are reaſonable, and may be proved, or defended by Reaſon againſt all <hi>Athe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſts</hi> or <hi>Infidels,</hi> &amp;c. She ſecures alſo the certainty of her Faith, by reſolving it into the Scriptures, the true Seat of Infallibility; and the belief of the Scriptures (on the other hand) into the Teſtimony of the Spirit of God, which confirmed it by Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles. So that by theſe Three Characters, of a True and Goſpel Faith, the Church to which I am now joined, doth not only profeſs, but practiſe it: True, the beſt Church and Religion may be diſcredited by its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, and that the Eſtabliſhed Religion as ſuch, is falſe, can never be wreſted out of the Mouths of thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and others, which ſeek and take occaſions to Blaſpheme it; till ſuch time as the compoſing our Differences, ſhall take away that occaſion which they have ſo unhappily given; and we take the Apoſtles advice, to the Epiſtle of <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. 28. to ſtand faſt in one Spirit, with one Mind, ſtriving toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Faith of the Goſpel, and in nothing terrified by our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; which to them is an evident token of Perdition, but to us of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and that of God. I know its poſſible (ſome may not only think, but ſay) that they may maintain Charity, notwithſtanding they break Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with an Eſtabliſhed Church: But <hi>Beloved,</hi> give me leave to tell, nay, to aſſure you that that is next to impoſſible to be done; for when Men's Differences are about Matters of Religion, then as I know by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Paſſion is apt to ſlide under that fair pretext, and lay claim to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience it ſelf; ſo that it becomes a piece of Zeal to be Uncharitable: But give me leave to premiſe, that it's not ſufficient for any Man or Woman's Repoſe, to ſay that they are acted by Conſcience, which is no other than ones preſent Perſwaſion. Conſcience it ſelf then muſt needs lie at the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of every thing that has Power to perſwade it<hi>:</hi> and hence oftentimes it comes to paſs that whilſt Conſcience acts ſuch it ſelf, (as I, and I do not doubt but many of you have obſerved) is acted by Paſſions, and Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, &amp; then what has, muſt, or will become of the Regularity of what ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:180263:8"/>
have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. I am fully perſwaded, that every Chriſtian deteſts the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of being ſawyed in Matters of Religion; either by Intereſt or P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>viſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs, or Pride, or Appetites, or Averſions, or ſomething that is and has been either avowedly Evil, or Shamefully Weak.</p>
            <p>But now I ſhallnot raſhly charge any with being ſwaied with ſuch, tho' I have great Reaſon to ſuſpect that all theſe before-mentioned, have found ways to paſs into ſome, nay, I may ſay, into too many Men and Womens Conſciences, and there act as ſecurely as behind a Curtain; yea, even at that time when ſuch were and are ready to deteſt them in their naked Appearances: To confirm which Truth, I will appeal not only to mine own, but ſome others undeniable Experiences, themſelves being Judges; Nay, have none of you here ever heard of, nor known any who out of Wanto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs of Wit, and Affectation of Singularity, have made a perfect new Model of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> by making a <hi>God</hi> without <hi>Eternity,</hi> a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> without Satisfaction, and an <hi>Hell</hi> without Torments; theſe forſooth, did firſt admite their Scheme, and then believed it, and ſo became Maſters of a <hi>Sect;</hi> and thus their Vanity paſſed into <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Others there have been, and are of a Moroſer Temper and Complexion, which falling as it were into diſlike with that Sweetneſs <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> obliges to, and thoſe <hi>Sacraments</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> which are the Tyes of Union, and that <hi>Goſpel</hi> that ſo inceſantly preſſes it: Theſe (as I know by former Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, being one of them) verily have believed that the very <hi>Goſpel-Inſtitutions</hi> are but Types and Shadows; and that every Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man has a <hi>ſurer Word of Propheſie</hi> within Themſelves, and that <hi>God</hi> muſt be ſerved without all poſſitive Commandments or Ordinances, &amp;c. Theſe you (as well as I) know have ſprung into a numerous <hi>Sect;</hi> and thus <hi>Completion</hi> and <hi>Humour</hi> have paſſed, and doth paſs into <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Others there are which you cannot but have heard of, whoſe <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> has firſt inclined them to Teach, and then the Succeſs of their <hi>Doctrine</hi> has temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them to believe that the Merits of Humane <hi>Piety</hi> may be transferred from Perſon to Perſon, and that the Fruits of <hi>Repentance</hi> may be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed at a Price: So having let their Minds grow Groſs and Carnal, and then finding themſelves either too much at Loſs in their Devotions, to a Pure and Inviſible <hi>Being,</hi> have introduced ſenſible Objects of Worſhip, and humane Mediators, to whom they might addreſs both with more Boldneſs and Careleſneſs<hi>:</hi> And thus both <hi>Avarice</hi> and <hi>Beaſtiality</hi> have paſſed and do paſs into <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others there are, and have been, which being fond of ſome Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and having no other Foundation to build upon, have (by their Dreams and vain Imaginations) made them Canonical; and being of a temper more Zealous, and Fierce, and having perſwaded themſelves that all is Sacred that they do for the Advancement of their own Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and ſo have allowed and practiſed <hi>Perſecutions, Murders,</hi> and <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages;</hi> And thought (as <hi>Saul,</hi> which afterward was named <hi>Paul)</hi> that in ſo doing, they did God good Service. Thus Fondneſs and Cruelty have Paſſed into Conſcience.—Others there are, and have been, which being uneaſie in their Worldly Circumſtances, and then reflecting upon that Myſterious Intimation that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould ſome time Reign alone upon Earth, have (as they were willing) believed that that Time was near Accompliſhed, and thereupon have cryed down all <hi>Worldly Government</hi> as <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> hoping thereby to ſet up <hi>King Jeſus,</hi> and themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; And thus Diſcontent, has paſſed into <hi>Conſcience.—</hi>But to be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:180263:8"/>
brief. Others there have been, and alſo are, which have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> devoted to an Averſion to the <hi>Church</hi> eſtabliſhed, (as I was) even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their Youth, being warned to avoid it, and not to have any particular Communion with it; on the Peril of their Souls, being told (as I was) that it was <hi>Antichriſtian, Popiſh, Socinian,</hi> or <hi>Pelagian;</hi> being made to believe that it's Monſtrous, without ever being ſuffered to Examine or Underſtand it; And being thus bred under Maſters better skilled in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming than Proving, have been alſo taught, that the moſt commendable <hi>Faith</hi> is that which ſwallows All Things without any Examination; and that the more Reaſon one hears againſt ones Self, the more Meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous is and will be ones obſtinacy. And thus not only Curioſity, but Prejudice alſo, and Cruelty have paſſed into <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what can or ſhall I ſay more, if both Men and Womens Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, Paſſions, Follies, Prejudices, Fondneſſes, Averſions, Wiſhes and Dreams, both may and have paſſed into <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and preſcribed and governed there, as by theſe you may underſtand; and ſome, I doubt not, here may by undeniable Experience know; Nay, it has been (by many as well as my ſelf) obſerved that the Matters which theſe of the <hi>Reformed Church</hi> differ about, are very ſmall; and the Animoſities both have been and are generally the higher, and greater: For to our Shame be it ſpoken, the ſmaller the Diſtance, or Difference, the wider the Breach; inſomuch that moſt can live more Friendly with an <hi>Infidel,</hi> that differs in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of Worſhip, than with another <hi>Chriſtian</hi> that differs only in the Form: The Reaſon whereof, (as I conjecture, and judge) muſt be this; That when the Opinions of others are at a great diſtance from our own, then we look upon them as a ſimple Perſwaſion; but when they come near to ours, we look upon ſuch as a kind of Affront, preſuming that where the Diſtance is ſo little, it is not ſo much the Matter of Controverſie, as the Malice of the Party that keeps up the Difference: So that is a Prejudice which naturally inflames Men and Women to Revenge, and breeds as we find by woful Experience, even a Canker in <hi>Religion,</hi> which inſenſibly eats up the Spirit of it, which cauſed the Princely Prophet to ſay, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99. 9. <hi>The Zeal of thine Houſe hath eaten me—</hi>But waving all this, to proceed to the <hi>Second</hi> Particular, namely, What that <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> is which made, and will make any Blameleſs? Now give me leave to ſuppoſe, that that Man or Woman which breaks Communion with a true Church which is by Law eſtabliſhed, tho' they maintain all other Acts of <hi>Charity</hi> as much as poſſible, as to bear no Malice to any, to Cenſure none, to Pray for, and wiſh well to all; yet I can and muſt aſſure you, that indeed is to be <hi>Righteous before God;</hi> but yet far ſhort of the Duty in keeping all the <hi>Commandments,</hi> ſince that Duty of <hi>Brotherly Love,</hi> namely, that Love which one <hi>Chriſtian</hi> owes to another, is not expreſſed; For <hi>Brotherly</hi> love is not or at leaſt can't be ſhown but by Communicating in <hi>Religious Offices,</hi> viz. <hi>Breaking of Bread,</hi> and in <hi>Prayers,</hi> as the Primitive Fellowſhip of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> is expreſſed in Holy Scripture; which Offices in all Ages have been looked upon as the neceſſary Teſts and Symbols of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Love &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But alas<hi>!</hi> alas<hi>!</hi> Diviſion both is, and has been (as I know by Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) the Mother of a great many Evils: For what an Harveſt was, and is it (as I formerly found) to wily Seducers? and what a Rock to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable Minds; yea, what a Snare to Itching Ears, and what anopportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Men and Women of either wanton or peeviſh Fancies to ſow the Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of Confuſion: And what a Provocation to God to ſuffer, that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:180263:9"/>
they who can't agree with one another, ſhould ſometimes or other be ſuffered to be devoured one of another.—But <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Some, nay, many pretend that their differing, or diſſenting from a true and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Church, is becauſe they cannot Edifie, as they think, under the Churches Teachers; and that is the chief if not the only Reaſon, they do, or cannot communicate with her; thinking it almoſt impoſſible to edifie as much under her Teachers, as they do under thoſe that ſeperate from her. And what the true Reaſon of non-edifying is, I ſhall now inquire into; and that being now by me perceived, and to you related, I am afraid will prove a very ſcandalous Reaſon; for I find that its nothing but Prejudice that hinders their Edification: Prejudice I ſay, which would hinder ſome from Edifying, even under the Labours of an Angel: I am well aſſured that it hindred many from improving under the Labours of a God, much more then under either ſome Angels or Men; for without all doubt our <hi>bleſſed Lord</hi> was a moſt edifying Preacher, and yet its evident that a great many of thoſe that heard him were never the better, they were indeed ſuch which ſpread abroad III Characters, and entertained a mean opinion of him, calling him the <hi>Carpenter's Son, a Wine-bibber, a Friend of Publicans and Sinners,</hi> with which Prejudice they hindred not only them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but alſo others from edifying.</p>
            <p>And to conclude this Second Particuiar of my Text, give me leave once more to tell all ſuch, which (as I once did) do diſſent from the Church, in making ſuch ſlender, but gay, and plauſible Pretences, that if they, as I did once, think or imagine that theirs is the right and true Way. To which I Anſwer, That that is but bare Thought or Imagination, which they (as I once fooliſhly did) ſo eagerly contend for; and that which they now have, and do contemn, are all Poſſitive, and Divine Commands, and Ordinances; nay, were ſuch certain, that the Rules and Ways which they propoſe were in their judgment, better than thoſe of the eſtabliſhed Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet they may be as certain that Love and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are better than theſe: And granting that Humane Laws are now diſpenſable at pleaſure; yet I hope that none dare, or will think that the Laws of God (which require an Obedience not only to ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Ordinances, but to all to be blameleſs) are and may be diſpenſed with by us. True, all Opinions plead Scripture for what they ſay and do, and many pretend to Reaſon, and the moſt to Antiquity: Ages I muſt confeſs alters Judgments, and Affections changes the Thoughts and Imaginations, often ſhift the Scene, and what ſome calls Reaſon, has proved oftentimes a chain of Phantaſms; ſo that often many are guided by Prejudices, and over-ruled by Authority; or formed as I have ſhewn by Education, and ſo ſuck in their Opinions careleſly, or by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and are deeply ſettled before they have examined; yea, when they do examine, its but by halves; For they ſeeing &amp; know but few things, judge all the reſt by thoſe they know and ſee; ſo that ſuch do not either ſeek the Truth at all, or are unable to manage a due and impartial ſearch of it: Or when they ſtumble upon it, they do not know; or when it is in their ſight, they boggle, and are afraid, and ſo runs away from it, or elſe begins to daub it with vile Aſperſions, whilſt they catch only at Shadows, and grow fond of the Images of their own Fancies, crying up thoſe for Truth and Faith: Thus diſturbing Societies, and the Peace of Mankind, to gain Credit to their own fond Dreams and Fancies, being confident of their Opinions, and even hating thoſe which are not of their Perſwaſion. Thus forſaking a certain Duty for ſome doubtful and fooliſh Tenets. If theſe were but conſidered by all, Fondneſs towards Opinion would be leſſened, and Charity promoted, which is ſo neceſſary among all Chriſtians, which that it may come to paſs, God grant for Chriſt's ſake: AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
